Finding Aid for Wells Ira Bennett Papers 1916-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wells Ira Bennett Papers 1916-1965
Bennett, Wells Ira, 1888-
Architect, professor and dean of the College of Architecture and Design of the University of Michigan. Professional papers, notebooks, sketches and architectural plans, and files on specific building projects, including work on the Flint campus of the University of Michigan, automobile parking structures, and miscellaneous Ann Arbor and University of Michigan buildings; also records of various state and national architectural accreditation and registration boards, especially the Michigan State Board of Registration for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors; and photographs.
85577 Aa 2 Ac
3.4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Wells I. Bennett (donor no. 4636 ) and came to the library in 1969.
The collection is open for research.
The career of Wells Ira Bennett, professor and Dean of the College of Architecture and Design at The University of Michigan, was divided throughout between the academic and the practical, the traditional and the contemporary. Although most of Bennett's actual work was done in Michigan, his studies of the architectural implications of urban growth and development earned him a far broader reputation. His interests, as reflected in his writings, ranged from parking structures and low-cost housing to seaports and post-war Korean architecture. The papers in this collection date from 1916, the beginning of Bennett's career as an architect, and extend to his death in 1965.
As a graduate student and young professor at The University of Michigan, Bennett worked closely with Fiske Kimball, an architect then on the faculty of the University of Virginia. Their correspondence deals primarily with the Colonial architects and architecture of the Southern and Middle Atlantic States. While Kimball devoted his entire career to these traditional forms, Bennett soon moved on to more pragmatic contemporary, architectural concerns.
Following brief service as an architect with the War Department in 1918, Bennett became increasingly interested in low-cost, functional architecture. He toured Europe in 1932-1933, noting with particular interest the architecture of those countries which had undertaken extensive rebuilding programs after World War I. Bennett corresponded with his mentor Emil Lorch while on this trip, commenting not only upon architecture, but also upon European political, social and economic conditions. They discussed at length the impact of the current financial crisis upon education and compared its severity on the two continents. The collection includes the originals of Bennett's letters to Lorch, and copies of Lorch's replies.
A study of French housing conditions, conducted in 1933-1935 with the assistance of Madame A. Bonnaud of the Office Public d'Habitations de Departement de la Seine introduced Bennett to the issues of public housing and urban planning. Believing that an efficient housing program would promote economic recovery, and strongly opposed to government funded housing projects, Bennett accepted a position as architectural advisor to the Prebilt Housing Corporation, one of the early private ventures in American prefabricated housing. His correspondence with Ernest Pavey the company's director traces the industry's development from the earliest idea through the point of actual production, dealing particularly with the need to combine "land planning, careful financing and the latest technical developments." While working on this project, Bennett began to explore the potential uses of steel in building. He became fascinated with this medium and continued to use it throughout his career.
As a result of his work in housing, Bennett's interests expanded into urban and campus planning. He was appointed to the Ann Arbor City Planning Commission in 1935 and did extensive work on parking structures and urban traffic flow in the early fifties. He worked as an advisor to the planning committee of the Flint College and Cultural Center in 1957458 and wrote several articles on Flint's industrial history.
Throughout these years Bennett continued to work as an architect in Ann Arbor. The collection includes a list of his specific works and detailed accounts of the work on his own home and the E.R. Sunderland residence. He maintained a strong interest in the architectural history of the University. A letter to James M. Babcock (April 27, 1964) identifies the architectural firms responsible for various early University buildings and lists their other works in Michigan. In 1952, he published an article in Architecture, entitled "The Law Courts Building - University of Michigan."
As an educator, Bennett was concerned with the development of his profession and its schools. He served on numerous state and national accreditation boards, and was instrumental in developing guidelines for the standardization of licensing and accreditation practices.
Bennett became Dean of the College of Architecture and Design in 1937, the year in which the department was first granted the status of an independent college. In his efforts to improve the quality of education, he invited outstanding architects to the University for lectures, seminars and conferences. Among those who visited the University and with whom Bennett corresponded were R. Buckminster Fuller and Eric Mendelsohn.
After his retirement in 1957, Wells Bennett continued to travel and to write. His travels resulted in many comparative architectural studies and a special interest in the sea, ships and harbors. Bennett died in 1966.
The collection has been divided into the following series: Biographical materials; Correspondence; Writings; Organizations; Projects; Miscellaneous; Diaries and other bound materials; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Architects.; Architecture.; Automobile parking.; Bennett, Wells Ira, 1888-; Housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan. State Board of Registration for Architects, Professional Engineers, and Land Surveyors.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Flint.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Architecture.; Bennett, Wells Ira, 1888-; Buildings.; Flint (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Germany.; Italy.; Netherlands.; Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.); University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan--Flint.
Contributors:
Bonnaud, A., Madame.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-1983.; Gropius, Walter, 1883-1969.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Hughes, Talmadge Coates, 1887-1963.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), b. 1858.; Kimball, Fiske, 1888-1955.; Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.; Mendelsohn, Erich, 1887-1953.; Moore, Charles, 1855-1942.; Pavey, Ernest W.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Saarinen, Eliel, 1873-1950.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Drawings.; Photographs.
- Biographical materials
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1914-1965, 27 folders (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Lists of work from Mrs. Bennett (Box 1)
  - " Some Notes on Flint, Michigan", Manuscript copy (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Writings (probably by Wells Ira Bennett) (Box 2)
  - Published articles by Wells Ira Bennett (Box 2)
- Organizations
  - National Architectural Accrediting Board
    - Papers 1944-1946 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1949-1953 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1957 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Board of Registration for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors
    - Papers 1941-1943 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1954 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1955 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - National Architectural Accrediting Board
    - Factual Report of the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design 1951 (Box 2)
  - Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture
    - Evaluation of University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design
    - Executive Committee minutes 1936-1942 (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Architects' Association 1963 (Box 2)
  - Prebilt Housing Corporation-Miscellaneous papers 1933-1936 (Box 2)
- Projects
  - Survey of University Libraries 1957 (Box 2)
  - Campus maps and traffic flow plans (Box 2)
  - Parking Structures-Advertisements and Building information 1952-1955 (Box 2)
  - Flint College Campus Site Project
    - Reports and time schedules (Box 2)
    - Planning committee minutes 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - "Unistrut School Construction"-University of Michigan Research project (Box 2)
  - Wells Ira Bennett Residence 1952 (Box 2)
  - E.R. Sunderland Residence 1958 (Box 2)
  - House designed by Wells Ira Bennett (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Printed material (Box 2)
  - News clippings (Box 2)
  - Invitations and programs (Box 2)
  - Advertisements and catalogues (Box 2)
  - Notebooks 1961 (Box 2)
  - Architectural plans and drawings (Box 2)
  - Notes and drafts, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2)
- Diaries and other bound materials
  - " Building The University of Michigan, 1840-1942" (Box 3)
  - " Building The University of Michigan, 1840-1942" Illustrations (Folder Ac)
  - Travel diaries 1931-1933, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - Travel diary (Paris & London) April-June 1933 (Box 3)
  - Travel diary 1956 (Box 3)
  - Travel diary 1960 (Box 3)
  - Travel diary (Sicily) 1962 (Box 3)
  - Notebooks concerning houses designed, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan student notebooks of Sybil K. Wells 1914 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  Photos of European architecture (primarily in Berlin) taken about 1932, photos of the development of the University of Michigan-Flint campus, and photos relating to the Unistrut Corporation and the Unistrut building near the University of Michigan Architecture and Design Building.
  - Architecture circa 1932
    - Germany (primarily Berlin), 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Italy (Box 4)
    - Netherlands (Box 4)
  - Buckminster Fuller model 1949 (Box 4)
  - Drawings (Box 4)
  - Flint College and Cultural Center (Box 4)
  - Unistrut construction conference 1955 (Box 4)
  - Unistrut structural system 1950 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Bonnaud, A., Madame
August 22, 1933; October 21, 1933; November 20, 1933; December 19, 1933; January 14, 1934; January 13; 1934; January 8, 1934; February 18, 1934; September 28, 1934; January 29, 1935; April 4, 1935; June 26, 1935; July 31, 1935
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.
October 22, 1920; October 25, 1922; June 4, 1923; June 20, 1923; October 31, 1923; June 21, 1924
Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.
March 1, 1943; March 13, 1943
Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-
May 25, 1948; June 2, 1948; November 29, 1948; December 11, 1948; February 18, 1949; February 2, 1949; February 16, 1949; May 14, 1949; June 15, 1949; July 28, 1949; October 3, 1949; October 8, 1949; October 11, 1949; October 17, 1949; October 26, 1949; September 15, 1952 September 18, 1952; April 1, 1963; January 27, 1964
Gropius, Walter Adolf, 1883-1969.
April 16, 1940
Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-
June 10, 1960
Hughes, Talmadge Coates, 1887-1963.
May 28, 1947; February 24, 1959; February 20, 1959; February 24, 1959; September 25, 1961
Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey),1858-1927.
June 22, 1916; November 13, 1916
Kimball, Fiske, 1888-1955.
October 16, 1916; November 7, 1916; November 17, 1916; November 27, 1916; December 12, 1916; April 6, 1917; August 1, 1919; August 10, 1919; August 12, 1919; March 9, 1920; May 3, 1920; May 13, 1920
May 24, 1920; June 4, 1920; July 14, 1920; August 15, 1920; October 21, 1920; April 24, 1922; May 7, 1922; May 21, 1922; November 7, 1922; March 20, 1923; April 18, 1923; April 26, 1927
Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.
January 11, 1918; August 8, 1918; January 9, 1919; January 18, 1919; January 20, 1919; January 24, 1919
March 5, 1931; February 17, 1932; August 5, 1932; September 16, 1932; September 27, 1932; October 13, 1932 November 17, 1932; November 30, 1932; December 20, 1932; January 26
193 February 17, 1933; February 19, 1933; March 3, 1933; March 16, 1933; April 17, 1933; May 19, 1933; September 23, 1935; September 24, 1935; September 25, 1935; September 14, 1935
Mendelsohn, Erich, 1887-1953.
January 11, 1932; March 30, 1942; March 22, 1942; March 27, 1943
Moore, Charles, 1885-1942.
November 21, 1916
Pavey, Ernest W.
January 4, 1933; June 25, 1934; August 1933; September 1933; October, 1933; December 1933; January 1934; February 1, 1934; April 26, 1934; May 1934; June 25, 1934; July 9, 1934; September 1934; October 1934; November 1934
January 2, 1935; March 1935; April 1935; May 1935; June 1935; July 1935; August 1935,September 1935; October 1935; November 1935; December 1935
January 1936; February 1936; March 1936; April 15, 1936; June 1936; July 1936; August 1936; November 20, 1936; February 1937; March 2, 1937; July 1937
Ruthven,Alexander Grant,1882-1971.
January 29, 1930; December 11, 1935; April 25, 1936; April 27, 1936; May 18, 1936; May 19, 1936; May 20, 1936; June 1936; July 4, 1936; July 1, 1936; June 11, 1938; July 19, 1938; April 1, 1940
Saarinen, Eliel, 1873-1950.
May 15, 1940